Historic New England
Bowen family papers
- Papers of the Bowen family of Woodstock, Connecticut, 1774-1986, undated; MS006.01; Family papers (7 file boxes, 1 folio box, 5 oversize folders); Series I, Papers of the Bowen family of Woodstock, Connecticut, 1774-1986, undated (#1.1-5.5, 6.1-6.24, 6.28, 7.1-7.6, FB.1.1-FB.1.2, OB1.3, OB.2.3-OB.
  - Papers of Herbert Wolcott Bowen (1856-1927), 1884-1926; MS006.01.09; Personal papers (2 file boxes); Subseries I, Papers of Herbert Wolcott Bowen (1856-1927), 1884-1926 (#5.1-5.3, 5.5, 6.3-6.4), contains several of Bowen's published works; Yale Faculty in the Days of '78 contains inscription: "For Darling Sylvia from Herbert Wolcott Bowen, 1923." A 1907 letter regarding the shipment of materials to Caracas, Venezuela, is attached to the inside cover of Passing Thoughts [copy 1] (#5.1). Also included in the subseries is a 1925 brief regarding a proposed bill on bathing, boating and fishing in natural lakes and ponds, presented to the Judiciary Committee of the Connecticut Legislature (#6.3). The subseries is arranged chronologically. (HGO-02-105-A-E-301)
    - Printed material, 1884-1926; MS006.01.09.01; Publications (2 file boxes)
      - Verses, 1884; MS006.01.09.01.01 (Box 5, Folder 2)
      - International Law: A Simple Statement of Its Principles; includes loose items, 1896; MS006.01.09.01.02 (Box 5, Folder 3)
      - Passing Thoughts [2 copies]; includes letter re: shipment of materials to Caracas, Venezuela, May 18 [copy 1, front cover], 1902-1907; MS006.01.09.01.03 (Box 5, folder 1)
      - Smoke-Rings; includes brief re: proposed bill on bathing, boating and fishing in natural lakes and ponds presented to the Judiciary Committee of the Connecticut Legislature, February 12, 1921-1925; MS006.01.09.01.04 (Box 6, Folder 3)
      - Yale Faculty in the Days of '78 [2 copies]; includes inscription, 1923; MS006.01.09.01.05 (Box 6, Folder 4)
      - Recollections Diplomatic and Undiplomatic, 1926; MS006.01.09.01.06 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Papers of John Eliot Bowen (1858-1890), MS006.01.10; Personal papers (3 file boxes); Subseries J, Papers of John Eliot Bowen (1858-1890), 1890 (#3.5, 5.4, 6.5), contains pamphlets with Bowen's obituary, printed by the Independent newspaper, and a published memorial of Bowen's life printed privately by his siblings. The subseries is arranged alphabetically by record type. (HGO-02-105-A-E-301)
    - Pamphlets: Independent newspaper, obituary for John Eliot Bowen, January 9 [6 copies], 1890; MS006.01.10.01 (Box 6, Folder 5)
    - Printed material: Memorial of John Eliot Bowen [copy 1], 1890; MS006.01.10.02 (Box 3, folder 5)
    - Printed material: Memorial of John Eliot Bowen [copy 2], 1890; MS006.01.10.03 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Papers of Lucy Maria (Tappan) Bowen (1825-1863), 1849-1862; MS006.01.11; Personal papers (1 file box); Subseries K, Papers of Lucy Maria (Tappan) Bowen (1825-1863), 1849-1862 (#1.20-1.21), contains a series of correspondence between Bowen and orator Henry Ward Beecher (1813-1887). Also included in the subseries is a receipt for clothing. The subseries is arranged alphabetically by record type. (HGO-02-105-A-E-301)
    - Correspondence: Henry Ward Beecher (1813-1887) [photocopies], 1860-1862; MS006.01.11.01 (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - Receipt re: purchase of clothing, 1849; MS006.01.11.02 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Papers of Matthew Bowen (1724-1806), 1774-1973, predominant 1774-1789; MS006.01.12; Personal papers (2 file boxes); Subseries L, Papers of Matthew Bowen (1724-1806), 1774-1973 (bulk, 1774-1789) (#1.1, 2.4), contains an account book reflecting Bowen's lending and borrowing activities as a tradesman. Also included in the subseries is a letter from Karen N. McFarlan (Mrs. F. Warren McFarlan) of Belmont, Massachusetts, regarding her donation of the account book to Historic New England. The subseries is arranged alphabetically by record type. (HGO-02-105-A-E-301)
    - Account book; includes loose items, 1774-1928, predominant 1774-1789; MS006.01.12.01; NOTE: See #1.1 for item removed. (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - Letter from Karen N. McFarlan (Mrs. F. Warren McFarlan) of Belmont, Massachusetts, re: donation of the Matthew Bowen account book, June 20, 1973, undated; MS006.01.12.02; NOTE: Item removed from #2.4. (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Papers of Constance Holt (1879-1968), 1943-1968; MS006.01.13; Personal papers (1 file box); Subseries M, Papers of Constance Holt (1879-1968), 1943-1968 (#6.13-6.14), contains a 1968 will and World War II (1939-1945) ration books for food and heating oil. The subseries is arranged alphabetically by record type. (HGO-02-105-A-E-301)
    - Ration books, 1943-1945; MS006.01.13.01 (Box 6, folder 13)
    - Will, March 13 [photocopy], 1968; MS006.01.13.02 (Box 6, Folder 14)
  - Papers of George Chandler Holt (1843-1931), 1894-1929, undated; MS006.01.14; Personal papers (1 file box); Subseries N, Papers of George Chandler Holt (1843-1931), 1894-1929, undated (#6.8-6.12), contains a poem and two published works by Holt. The subseries also includes a bibliographical sketch for George Chandler Holt and for Hamilton Holt (1872-1951). The subseries is arranged alphabetically by record type, and thereunder chronologically. (HGO-02-105-A-E-301)
    - Biographical sketches: George Chandler Holt (1843-1931) and Hamilton Holt (1872-1951) [photocopies], undated; MS006.01.14.01 (Box 6, Folder 8)
    - Poem: "Volubilities of a Vegetarian," December 31, 1923; MS006.01.14.02 (Box 6, Folder 9)
    - Printed material, 1894-1929; MS006.01.14.03; publications (1 file box)
      - Lynching and Mobs, September 6, 1894; MS006.01.14.03.01 (Box 6, Folder 10)
      - Descendants and Relatives of Hiram Holt and Marian Chandler Holt, 1921; MS006.01.14.03.02 (Box 6, Folder 11)
      - Old Chandler Farm in Pomfret, 1929; MS006.01.14.03.03 (Box 6, Folder 12)
  - Papers of Henry Chandler Holt (1881-1955), 1905-1911; MS006.01.15; Personal papers (1 file box); Subseries O, Papers of Henry Chandler Holt (1881-1955), 1905-1911 (#6.15), contains a 1905 letter from the Southern Railway Company to Holt and a 1911 issue of the Yale '94 Gazette. (HGO-02-105-A-E-301)
    - Printed material: Yale '94 Gazette, November; includes letter from Southern Railway Company, December 2, 1905-1911; MS006.01.15.01 (Box 6, Folder 15)
  - Papers of Mary Louisa (Bowen) Holt (1848-1925), 1924-1925; MS006.01.16; Personal papers (1 file box); Subseries P, Papers of Mary Louisa (Bowen) Holt (1848-1925), 1924-1925 (#4.10), contains wills from 1924 and 1925. (HGO-02-105-A-E-301)
    - Wills, 1924-1925; MS006.01.16.01 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Papers of Sylvia Holt (1889-1945), 1932; MS006.01.17; Personal papers (1 file box); Subseries Q, Papers of Sylvia Holt (1889-1945), 1932 (#6.16), contains a 1932 will. (HGO-02-105-A-E-301)
    - Will, February 4 [photocopy], 1932; MS006.01.17.01 (Box 6, Folder 16)
  - Papers of Gardner Richardson (1884-1972), 1965; MS006.01.18; Personal papers (1 file box); Subseries R, Papers of Gardner Richardson (1884-1972), 1965 (#6.17), contains two extracts of Richardson's 1965 address entitled, "Roseland Park and Henry C. Bowen," delivered at the Putnam Rotary Club in Putnam, Connecticut. (HGO-02-105-A-E-301)
    - Printed material: "Roseland Park and Henry C. Bowen," extracts from an address delivered at the Putnam Rotary Club, Putnam, Connecticut, February 23 [2 copies], 1965; MS006.01.18.01 (Box 6, Folder 17)
  - Genealogical material, 1850, undated; MS006.01.19; Genealogy (2 file boxes, 1 folio box, 1 oversize folder); Subseries S, Genealogical material, 1850, undated (#6.18, 7.5-7.6, FB.1.1-FB.1.2, OB.3.7), contains two volumes noted as "ancestral tablets," which trace the Bowen family genealogy from the William Towne family; handwritten genealogical notes; an undated genealogical chart of the Henry Chandler Bowen (1813-1896) family; an 1850 census record for the Bowen family; a bound volume of the Bowen family genealogy with corresponding index; and an undated genealogical chart tracing the descendants of Bowen of Slade in Wales, Great Britain, United Kingdom. The subseries is arranged alphabetically by record type, and thereunder chronologically. (HGO-02-105-A-E-301; HGO-02-105-A-E-302; HGO-02-105-A-E-101; HGO-02-105-A-E-106)
    - Genealogy, MS006.01.19.01; 6 folders (Box 6, Folder 18; Box 7, Folders 5-6; Box FB.1, Folders 1-2; Box OB.1, Folder 2)
      - Ancestral tablets, William Towne family, book 1 (1601-1896), MS006.01.19.01.01 (Box 7, Folder 6)
      - Ancestral tablets, William Towne family, book 2 (1601-1864), MS006.01.19.01.02 (Box 7, Folder 5)
      - Bowen family genealogical material; includes Henry Chandler Bowen family genealogical chart and Bowen family census record [photocopy], MS006.01.19.01.03 (Box 6, Folder 18)
      - Bowen family record (1631-1874), MS006.01.19.01.04 (Box FB.1, Folder 1)
      - Bowen family reocrd (1631-1874), index of places; includes loose items, MS006.01.19.01.05 (Box FB.1, Folder 2)
      - Bowen of Slade, Oxwich Parish, Gower, Glamorganshire, Wales, Great Britain, family genealogical chart, MS006.01.19.01.06 (Box OB.1, Folder 2)
    - Ancestral tablets: William Towne family, book 1 (1601-1896), undated; MS006.01.19.02; NOTE: See #OB.2.5 for item removed [1896 newspaper] (Box 7, Folder 6)
    - Ancestral tablets: William Towne family, book 2 (1601-1864), undated; MS006.01.19.03 (Box 7, Folder 5)
    - Bowen family genealogical chart: Bowen of Slade, Oxwich Parish, Gower, Glamorganshire, Wales, Great Britain, United Kingdom, undated; MS006.01.19.04 (Box OB.3, Folder 7)
    - Bowen family genealogical material; includes undated Henry Chandler Bowen family genealogical chart and Bowen family census record [photocopy], 1850, undated; MS006.01.19.05; NOTE: Henry Chandler Bowen family: genealogical chart removed from #4.9 NOTE: 1850 census material removed from #6.23 (Box 6, Folder 18)
    - Bowen family record (1631-1874), undated; MS006.01.19.06; NOTE: See #FB.1.2 for items removed [index and loose material] (Box FB.1, Folder 1)
    - Bowen family record (1631-1874), index of places; includes loose material, undated; MS006.01.19.07; NOTE: Items removed from #FB.1.1 (Box FB.1, Folder 2)
  - Other Bowen family papers, 1806-1986, undated; MS006.01.20; Family papers (3 file boxes, 3 oversize folders); Subseries T, Other family papers, 1806-1986, undated (#2.1, 6.19-6.24, 6.28, 7.1, 7.3, OB.2.3-OB.2.5), contains a note referencing the key to the Roseland Cottage safe; correspondence regarding the paintings of artist Clara Soule (1834-1902); fragments of correspondence and financial records; a guest book from Roseland Cottage, which contains an 1894 ribbon for a summer outing; invitations to a circa 1890 Jenny Lind concert and an 1891 Fourth of July celebration at Roseland Cottage; a notebook entitled, "Nathan Martins' Book of Woodstock, Connecticut, 1806," which contains handwritten poems, other writings, and mathematical calculations; and printed material. Also included in the subseries are items removed from the lap desk of Elizabeth Tappan (dates unknown), which is held by Historic New England (#6.28). Contents of the lap desk include a calling/visiting card for an Ethel P. Bowen (dates unknown); a trade card for a Brooklyn wig maker; invitations to a "Boy's Prayer Meeting;" a 1922 Valentine to a "Mrs. White of Boston;" and a handwritten verse and envelope addressed to Henry Bowen White (dates unknown). The subseries is arranged alphabetically by record type, and thereunder chronologically. (HGO-02-105-A-E-301; HGO-02-105-A-E-302; HGO-02-105-A-E-106)
    - Correspondence: letter re: key to safe at Roseland Cottage, 1945; MS006.01.20.01; NOTE: Item removed from #1.16. (Box 6, Folder 19)
    - Correspondence: letters re: paintings of Clara Soule (1834-1902), July 25, 1986; MS006.01.20.02 (Box 6, Folder 20)
    - Financial records, unidentified, 1847-1853; MS006.01.20.03 (Box 6, Folder 21)
    - Guest book: Roseland Cottage, Woodstock, Connecticut Guest book: Roseland Cottage, Woodstock, Connecticut, 1870-1984; includes loose items and a ribbon: "C.E.A. Summer Outing, Roseland Park, August 23, 1984", MS006.01.20.04 (Box 7, Folder 3)
    - Invitations re: parties at Roseland Cottage, Woodstock, Connecticut, 1890-1891; MS006.01.20.05 (Box 6, Folder 22)
    - Notebook: Nathan Martins' book of Woodstock, Connecticut, 1806; MS006.01.20.06 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Other papers, fragments; includes clipping, 1851-1986, undated; MS006.01.20.07; NOTE: See #6.18 for item removed [1850 Bowen family census]. (Box 6, Folder 23)
    - Other papers: items removed from the lap desk of Elizabeth Tappan (dates unknown), 1922, undated; MS006.01.20.08; NOTE: See SPNEA furniture collection #1974.370, Museum Collection, for Elizabeth Tappan's portable desk (Box 6, folder 28)
    - Printed material: Windham County Transcript, "The Great Celebration," July 6; includes speeches by Henry Ward Beecher, Theodore Tilton, Governors Buckingham and Cleveland, 1865; MS006.01.20.09; NOTE: CONTAINS FRAGILE MATERIAL. (Box OB.2, Folder 4)
    - Printed material: Independent newspaper, twenty-first year commemorative issue, December 2, 1869; MS006.01.20.10; NOTE: CONTAINS FRAGILE MATERIAL. (Box OB.2, Folder 3)
    - Printed material: Woodstock Centennial Recorder, September 10; includes historical address delivered by Clarence Winthrop Bowen (1852-1935), 1886; MS006.01.20.11; NOTE: CONTAINS FRAGILE MATERIAL. (Box OB.2, Folder 4)
    - Printed material: Independent newspaper, February 20, 1896; MS006.01.20.12; NOTE: Item removed from #7.6. NOTE: CONTAINS FRAGILE MATERIAL. (Box OB.2, Folder 5)
    - Printed material: Continental Insurance Company of New York, 1853-1905: A Historical Sketch, MS006.01.20.13 (Box 7, Folder 1)
    - Printed material: bylaws and charter of the Woodstock Academy, Woodstock, Connecticut, September [3 copies]; includes Woodstock Academy Gleaner, 1901-1934; MS006.01.20.14; NOTE: See also #1.9 for related material. (Box 6, Folder 24)
- Papers relating to the construction of Roseland Cottage, Woodstock, Connecticut, 1845-1969, undated, predominant 1845-1851; MS006.02; Business records (3 file boxes, 1 oversize folder); Series II, Papers relating to the construction of Roseland Cottage, Woodstock, Connecticut, 1845-1969, undated (bulk: 1845-1851) (#6.25-6.27, 8.1-8.17, 12.15, OB.3.8), is divided into four categories: contracts and specifications; correspondence; financial records; and other material. The contracts and specifications include two drafts and a signed agreement between Henry Chandler Bowen (1813-1896) and contractor Samuel Underwood regarding construction materials for Roseland Cottage and an adjoining barn; specifications of architect Joseph Collins Wells (1814-1860) regarding the carpentry and masonry work for Roseland Cottage and the barn; and floor plans for an addition to the barn. The correspondence contains letters received by Henry Chandler Bowen (1813-1896) regarding the construction of Roseland Cottage. Among the letters are contractor Samuel Underwood's request to be released from his contract; letters from contractor Edwin Eaton detailing the work progress on the construction of Roseland Cottage; and Eaton's letters regarding his decision to hire a Mr. Taylor of Brooklyn, New York, to complete the masonry work and a Mr. Joy of Worcester, Massachusetts, as foreman. Included in the financial records are bills and receipts; drafts of checks; payment made to laborers; and payments for the purchase of construction supplies for Roseland Cottage, which were kept by Henry Chandler Bowen (1813-1896), Lewis Chamberlin, and Edwin Eaton. Also included in the series is a collection of papers entitled, "Reminiscences of Roseland Cottage," which describes the rooms and interior furnishings at Roseland Cottage as recalled by an Anna Mellon; photographs taken of paintings that were once inside Roseland Cottage (including several portraits of Benjamin Franklin, 1706-1790); and clippings reflecting life at Roseland Cottage. The series is arranged alphabetically by record type, and thereunder chronologically. (HGO-02-105-A-E-301; HGO-02-105-A-E-302; HGO-02-105-A-E-106)
  - Agreement between Henry Chandler Bowen and contractor, Samuel Underwood, re: construction of a house and barn, October 13, 1845 [2 copies]; includes drafts [2 copies], MS006.02.01.01 (Box 6, Folder 25)
  - Specifications of Joseph C. Wells, architect, re: carpentry [2 copies] and masonary work [1 copy] on the house, 1845, MS006.02.01.02; Bowen family papers (MS006) Series II, Papers relating to the construction of Roseland Cottage, Woodstock, Connecticut, 1845-1969, undated (bulk: 1845-1851) (#6.25-6.27, 8.1-8.17, OB.1.4-OB.1.5), contains agreements and contracts (includes drafts); bills and receipts; building and construction specifications; correspondence; design and floor plans; drafts of checks; work account records; photographs; clippings; and a collection of papers describing the rooms at Roseland Cottage. The series is divided into three sections: contracts and specifications, financial records, and other materials. Contracts and specifications includes two drafts and a signed agreement between Henry Chandler Bowen and contractor, Samuel Underwood, regarding the furnishing of materials for construction of Roseland Cottage and an adjoining barn; specifications of architect, John C. Wells, for the carpentry and masonry work at Roseland Cottage and for the construction of the barn; and design and floor plans for the addition to the barn. The correspondence contains letters received by Henry Chandler Bowen relating to the construction work on Roseland Cottage. Several of the letters are from contractor, Samuel Underwood, requesting to be released from his contract; and other letters are from contractor, Edwin Eaton, detailing the work progress on the construction of Roseland Cottage and his decision to hire a Mr. Taylor of Brooklyn, New York, to complete the masonry work and a Mr. Joy of Worcester, Massachusetts, as foreman. The financial records include bills and receipts; drafts of checks; and work account records regarding the payment of laborers and the purchase of supplies associated with the construction of Roseland Cottage; the records were kept by Henry Chandler Bowen, Lewis Chamberlin, and Edwin Eaton. A collection of papers referred to as "Reminiscences of Roseland Cottage," describing the interior furnishings and rooms at Roseland Cottage, as recalled by Anna Mellon; photographs of a collection of paintin gs at Roseland Cottage (includes several photographs of Benjamin Franklin); and newspaper clippings relating to Roseland Cottage and its inhabitants, comprise the section of other materials. The series is arranged alphabetically by section, and thereunder chronologically. (Box 6, Folder 26)
  - Specifications of Joseph C. Wells, architect, re: construction of the barn, 1845, MS006.02.01.03; Bowen family papers (MS006) Series II, Papers relating to the construction of Roseland Cottage, Woodstock, Connecticut, 1845-1969, undated (bulk: 1845-1851) (#6.25-6.27, 8.1-8.17, OB.1.4-OB.1.5), contains agreements and contracts (includes drafts); bills and receipts; building and construction specifications; correspondence; design and floor plans; drafts of checks; work account records; photographs; clippings; and a collection of papers describing the rooms at Roseland Cottage. The series is divided into three sections: contracts and specifications, financial records, and other materials. Contracts and specifications includes two drafts and a signed agreement between Henry Chandler Bowen and contractor, Samuel Underwood, regarding the furnishing of materials for construction of Roseland Cottage and an adjoining barn; specifications of architect, John C. Wells, for the carpentry and masonry work at Roseland Cottage and for the construction of the barn; and design and floor plans for the addition to the barn. The correspondence contains letters received by Henry Chandler Bowen relating to the construction work on Roseland Cottage. Several of the letters are from contractor, Samuel Underwood, requesting to be released from his contract; and other letters are from contractor, Edwin Eaton, detailing the work progress on the construction of Roseland Cottage and his decision to hire a Mr. Taylor of Brooklyn, New York, to complete the masonry work and a Mr. Joy of Worcester, Massachusetts, as foreman. The financial records include bills and receipts; drafts of checks; and work account records regarding the payment of laborers and the purchase of supplies associated with the construction of Roseland Cottage; the records were kept by Henry Chandler Bowen, Lewis Chamberlin, and Edwin Eaton. A collection of papers referred to as "Reminiscences of Roseland Cottage," describing the interior furnishings and rooms at Roseland Cottage, as recalled by Anna Mellon; photographs of a collection of paintin gs at Roseland Cottage (includes several photographs of Benjamin Franklin); and newspaper clippings relating to Roseland Cottage and its inhabitants, comprise the section of other materials. The series is arranged alphabetically by section, and thereunder chronologically. (Box 6, Folder 27)
  - Plans for addition to the barn, undated [photocopies], MS006.02.01.04; Bowen family papers (MS006) Series II, Papers relating to the construction of Roseland Cottage, Woodstock, Connecticut, 1845-1969, undated (bulk: 1845-1851) (#6.25-6.27, 8.1-8.17, OB.1.4-OB.1.5), contains agreements and contracts (includes drafts); bills and receipts; building and construction specifications; correspondence; design and floor plans; drafts of checks; work account records; photographs; clippings; and a collection of papers describing the rooms at Roseland Cottage. The series is divided into three sections: contracts and specifications, financial records, and other materials. Contracts and specifications includes two drafts and a signed agreement between Henry Chandler Bowen and contractor, Samuel Underwood, regarding the furnishing of materials for construction of Roseland Cottage and an adjoining barn; specifications of architect, John C. Wells, for the carpentry and masonry work at Roseland Cottage and for the construction of the barn; and design and floor plans for the addition to the barn. The correspondence contains letters received by Henry Chandler Bowen relating to the construction work on Roseland Cottage. Several of the letters are from contractor, Samuel Underwood, requesting to be released from his contract; and other letters are from contractor, Edwin Eaton, detailing the work progress on the construction of Roseland Cottage and his decision to hire a Mr. Taylor of Brooklyn, New York, to complete the masonry work and a Mr. Joy of Worcester, Massachusetts, as foreman. The financial records include bills and receipts; drafts of checks; and work account records regarding the payment of laborers and the purchase of supplies associated with the construction of Roseland Cottage; the records were kept by Henry Chandler Bowen, Lewis Chamberlin, and Edwin Eaton. A collection of papers referred to as "Reminiscences of Roseland Cottage," describing the interior furnishings and rooms at Roseland Cottage, as recalled by Anna Mellon; photographs of a collection of paintin gs at Roseland Cottage (includes several photographs of Benjamin Franklin); and newspaper clippings relating to Roseland Cottage and its inhabitants, comprise the section of other materials. The series is arranged alphabetically by section, and thereunder chronologically. (Box OB.1, Folder 4)